<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<post>
  <title>Mastering Saga Pattern for Microservices: Best Practices and Solutions</title>
  <excerpt>Learn the best practices and solutions for mastering saga pattern in microservices. Stand out from the competition with our comprehensive guide.</excerpt>
  <date>2023-04-30</date>
  <categories>
    <category>Design pattern</category>
    <category>Programming</category>
  </categories>
  <tags>
    <tag>Design pattern</tag>
    <tag>Microservices</tag>
    <tag>Saga</tag>
  </tags>
  <author>
    <name>Alina</name>
    <picture>/assets/blog/authors/alina.jpeg</picture>
  </author>
  <content>
  <![CDATA[<!-- wp:image {"id":73,"sizeSlug":"full","linkDestination":"none"} -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img src="/assets/blog/posts/imgs/understanding-saga.jpeg" alt="Saga pattern illustrated " class="wp-image-73"/></figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Saga pattern is a design pattern that has revolutionized the way we coordinate multiple transactions or operations in a distributed system. It is based on the principle of using sagas, which are sequences of local transactions, to ensure consistency across all components involved in the process. The saga-based approach is particularly useful in scenarios such as booking orders, where multiple components like API gateway, orders component, and payment component need to work together seamlessly.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>To implement a saga-based approach, it is essential to prepare a protocol that outlines the sequence of steps involved in the process. For instance, the protocol for booking an order might include steps like "put order," "reserve inventory," "charge payment," and so on. This helps coordinate sagas across different components and ensures that each transaction is executed successfully.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The design patterns used in saga pattern make it possible to achieve consistency even when there are failures during the process. This means that if one component fails during a transaction, other components can still continue with their tasks without affecting the entire process.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading -->
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Understanding Saga Pattern: An Overview</h2>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:heading {"level":3} -->
<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Saga Pattern: An Overview</h3>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Saga pattern is an architectural pattern used to manage long-lived transactions in a distributed system. It helps to ensure data consistency across multiple services by breaking down a complex transaction into smaller, more manageable steps called saga workflow. In this section, we will discuss the different components of saga patterns and how they work together to achieve data consistency.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading {"level":3} -->
<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Saga Workflow</h3>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Saga patterns involve multiple participants, each responsible for carrying out a specific step in the saga workflow. The saga workflow is a sequence of steps that need to be executed in order to complete a transaction. Each step modifies the state of the system and generates events that trigger subsequent steps.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The saga workflow can be visualized as a directed acyclic graph (DAG), where each node represents a step and each edge represents the causal relationship between steps. The DAG can have multiple entry points and exit points, depending on the requirements of the transaction.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading {"level":3} -->
<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Saga Participants</h3>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Each participant in the saga workflow is responsible for executing a specific step and generating events that trigger subsequent steps. Participants are autonomous services that communicate with each other through messages.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Saga Participants can be implemented using different technologies and programming languages, as long as they conform to the messaging protocol defined by the saga architecture pattern. Saga Participants can also be scaled horizontally to handle large volumes of transactions.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading {"level":3} -->
<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Saga Log</h3>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The <strong>saga</strong> log is a persistent storage mechanism used to record the state of the transaction and ensure that all participants are aware of any changes. The log contains information about each step executed by each participant, including its input parameters, output parameters, and status.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The saga log is updated atomically after each step execution, ensuring that all participants see consistent views of the system state. The log can also be used for auditing purposes or for replaying failed transactions.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading {"level":3} -->
<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Saga Execution Controller</h3>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The saga execution controller is responsible for coordinating the saga workflow and ensuring that all participants complete their tasks successfully. The controller receives messages from participants and updates the saga log accordingly.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>If any participant fails to complete its task, the saga execution controller can trigger compensating actions to undo any changes made by previous participants and restore the system to its previous state. Compensating actions are defined for each step in the workflow and are executed in reverse order.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The saga execution controller can also handle timeouts or other exceptional conditions that may occur during the transaction. If a timeout occurs, the controller can trigger compensating actions to undo any changes made by previous participants and abort the transaction.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading -->
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Two-Phase Commit (PC) Pattern: Understanding the Basics</h2>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The Two-Phase Commit (PC) Pattern is a protocol used to ensure that all participating databases in a distributed transaction either commit or rollback the transaction. This pattern is essential for maintaining data consistency across multiple databases, especially when dealing with complex transactions. In this section, we will delve into the basics of the Two-Phase Commit (PC) Pattern and explore its two phases: the prepare phase and the commit phase.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading {"level":3} -->
<h3 class="wp-block-heading">The Prepare Phase</h3>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>During the prepare phase, each database involved in the transaction prepares to commit by recording a log of the changes made to its data. This log serves as a record of what changes were made so that they can be committed or rolled back later on. Once all databases have prepared to commit, they send a message to their respective coordinator indicating that they are ready.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The coordinator then waits until it receives messages from all participating databases before proceeding with the next step. If any database fails to respond during this phase, then it is assumed that there was an error and the entire transaction is rolled back.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading {"level":3} -->
<h3 class="wp-block-heading">The Commit Phase</h3>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Once all databases have successfully completed their preparation phase, the coordinator sends a message to each database asking them if they are ready to commit. If all databases respond with a positive response, then the coordinator sends out another message telling them to commit their changes permanently.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>If any database responds negatively during this phase, then it means that there was an error somewhere along the line and that particular database needs to roll back its changes. The coordinator sends out another message telling all other participating databases to roll back as well.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading {"level":3} -->
<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Benefits of Using Two-Phase Commit (PC) Pattern</h3>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Using this pattern ensures that every participating database has agreed on whether or not they should proceed with committing or rolling back their changes. It also guarantees that no matter what happens during this process – such as network failures or server crashes – data consistency will always be maintained across all involved parties.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading {"level":3} -->
<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Examples of Two-Phase Commit (PC) Pattern</h3>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>One example of where this pattern is used is in distributed systems that require data consistency across multiple databases. For instance, in an online banking system, a user may transfer funds from one account to another. The transaction involves multiple databases – the user's account database and the recipient's account database.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>In such a scenario, if one of the databases fails to commit or roll back its changes, then it could result in inconsistencies that could lead to serious problems such as overdrawn accounts or lost transactions. This is why using the Two-Phase Commit (PC) Pattern is crucial for maintaining data consistency and ensuring that all participating parties are on the same page.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading {"level":3} -->
<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Statistics Proving the Effectiveness of Two-Phase Commit (PC) Pattern</h3>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>According to a <a href="https://15445.courses.cs.cmu.edu/fall2021/slides/22-distributedoltp.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a> conducted by researchers at Carnegie Mellon University, using the <a href="https://martinfowler.com/articles/patterns-of-distributed-systems/two-phase-commit.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Two-Phase Commit</a> (PC) Pattern can significantly reduce the likelihood of data inconsistencies occurring during distributed transactions. The study found that when compared to other protocols such as Three-Phase Commit (3PC), which requires an additional round-trip message exchange between coordinator and participant, Two-Phase Commit (PC) was more efficient and less prone to errors.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading -->
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Identifying the Problem: Context and Issues with PC</h2>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The problem with using a 2pc (two-phase commit) protocol in a database is that it can lead to issues with customer service, particularly their preferences and data are stored in the site's own database. However, if the centralized controller handling the 2pc protocol fails or needs to be changed, this can cause problems with the customer's order and potentially lead to lost sales.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>One solution to this problem is to use the saga pattern. The saga pattern allows for more flexibility in handling events and changes to the system. With the saga pattern, each service involved in the transaction can handle its own part of the process, reducing the risk of failure and improving overall reliability.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading {"level":3} -->
<h3 class="wp-block-heading">The problem with the 2pc protocol</h3>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>To better understand why using a 2pc protocol can be problematic for businesses, let's take an example of an e-commerce website where users can purchase products online. When a user adds an item to their cart and checks out, several services are involved in processing their order. These services may include payment processing, inventory management, shipping logistics, and more.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>In a traditional 2pc protocol setup, all of these services would need to coordinate with one another through a centralized controller that manages transactions across all services involved. This means that if any one service experiences an issue or needs to be updated or replaced, it could cause delays or failures across all other services involved in that transaction.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>For instance, imagine that there is an issue with payment processing while a user is trying to complete their purchase on an e-commerce website. In this scenario, if any one service experiences an issue or needs updating or replacing during this transaction process then it could cause delays or failures across all other services involved in that transaction leading up to lost sales.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>However, by implementing a saga pattern into such systems we could avoid such scenarios as each service will have its own event log which will maintain its state and can handle its own part of the process. This would reduce the risk of failure and improve overall reliability.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading {"level":3} -->
<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Using a service that supports saga pattern</h3>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>By using <strong>AWS</strong> or other services that support the saga pattern, businesses can improve their customer service and reduce the risk of lost sales due to technical issues. This can also help to improve overall data management and make it easier to track customer orders and preferences over time.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><strong>AWS</strong> provides a number of tools that support the saga pattern, such as Amazon Simple Workflow Service (SWF) which allows developers to build applications with distributed workflows. SWF manages task execution across multiple services, making it easier to coordinate complex processes like order fulfillment or payment processing.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Another tool provided by <strong>AWS</strong> is Amazon EventBridge, which enables developers to build event-driven architectures for their applications. With EventBridge, developers can define custom events that trigger specific actions within their application. This makes it easy to handle changes in system state or user behavior without requiring manual intervention from developers.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>In addition to <strong>AWS</strong>, there are other services available that support the saga pattern such as Apache Camel Saga EIP (Enterprise Integration Pattern). Apache Camel Saga EIP is an open-source integration framework that supports the saga pattern for building resilient microservices-based applications.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading -->
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Disadvantages of Saga Pattern and the Pitfalls of Using PC</h2>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>While the Saga pattern has many advantages, it also has its fair share of disadvantages. In this section, we will discuss some of the pitfalls that come with using the Saga pattern and a Process Coordinator (PC).</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading {"level":3} -->
<h3 class="wp-block-heading">The Complexity of Implementing and Maintaining Saga Pattern</h3>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>One significant disadvantage of implementing the Saga pattern is its complexity. The Saga pattern involves coordinating multiple transactions across different services or <a href="/microservices-design-patterns-top-10/">microservices</a>. This coordination can be challenging to implement and maintain, requiring a high level of technical expertise.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Moreover, as systems grow in complexity, so does the difficulty in maintaining them. With each additional service or microservice added to a system, the number of interactions between them increases exponentially. As such, keeping track of all these interactions can become incredibly difficult.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading {"level":3} -->
<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Performance Issues and Potential Bottlenecks</h3>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Another disadvantage is that using a persistent storage mechanism such as a database can introduce performance issues and potential bottlenecks. Since each transaction in the saga needs to be persisted before moving on to the next one, this can cause delays in processing time.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Furthermore, if there are any issues with the database or other persistent storage mechanisms used by the saga, it could lead to significant problems for the entire system.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading {"level":3} -->
<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Difficulty Designing and Testing Compensation Logic</h3>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Compensation logic is another aspect that makes implementing Sagas challenging. The compensation logic required in Sagas ensures that if any part of a transaction fails at any point during execution, all changes made up until that point are rolled back.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Designing compensation logic requires careful consideration since it must account for every possible scenario where something might go wrong during execution. Additionally, testing compensation logic can be difficult since it requires simulating various failure scenarios to ensure everything works as expected.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Single Point Of Failure When Using A Process Coordinator (PC)</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>When working with Sagas, you'll often use a Process Coordinator (PC) to manage transactions across different services or microservices. However, using a PC can introduce a single point of failure and reduce the overall reliability of the system.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>If the PC fails, it could cause significant problems for the entire system since all transactions would come to a halt. Additionally, if there are any issues with communication between services or microservices, this could also lead to problems.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading {"level":3} -->
<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Examples of Pitfalls in Saga Pattern</h3>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>To illustrate further some of the pitfalls that come with implementing Sagas, let's look at some examples.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Suppose you have an e-commerce website where customers can place orders and pay for them online. When a customer places an order, several services need to work together to fulfill that order. These services might include inventory management, payment processing, shipping logistics, and more.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Using Sagas allows you to coordinate these different services so that they work together seamlessly. However, suppose there is an issue with payment processing during order fulfillment. In that case, compensation logic must be triggered to roll back any changes made up until that point.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Testing this compensation logic can be challenging since it requires simulating various failure scenarios such as failed payments or network outages.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Another example is when using Sagas in a travel booking application. Suppose a user books a flight and hotel reservation through your application. In that case, multiple services need to work together to ensure everything goes smoothly.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>However, if there is an issue with one of these services during execution - say the hotel reservation service goes down - then compensation logic needs to be triggered to roll back any changes made up until that point.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading -->
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Implementing Saga Choreography Pattern: A Step-by-Step Guide</h2>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:heading {"level":3} -->
<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Defining the Saga Execution Coordinator</h3>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>In implementing the choreography pattern, the saga execution coordinator plays a crucial role in ensuring that the transaction is completed successfully. The coordinator is responsible for managing the overall saga process and coordinating the actions of each service involved in the transaction.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The saga execution coordinator communicates with each service directly to determine whether a particular action has been completed successfully or not. If an action fails, the coordinator initiates compensating actions to undo any changes made during previous steps and ensure that the transaction remains consistent.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading {"level":3} -->
<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Using AWS Step Functions</h3>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:image {"sizeSlug":"large"} -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img src="https://d2908q01vomqb2.cloudfront.net/1b6453892473a467d07372d45eb05abc2031647a/2021/06/21/Screenshot-2021-06-21-at-15.40.44.png" alt=""/></figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>One way to implement the choreography pattern is by using AWS Step Functions. This fully managed service makes it easy to build and run applications that use long-running workflows. It provides a visual workflow editor and integrates with other AWS services to simplify the development process.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading {"level":3} -->
<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Breaking Down the Booking Process</h3>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>To illustrate how the choreography pattern works, let's consider an example of a booking process for a hotel reservation. This process involves several services, including a customer service, a room service, and a payment service.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The booking process starts when a customer requests to book a room at a hotel. The customer's request is sent to the customer service, which checks availability and pricing for a particular room type.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>If there are available rooms, then the customer can proceed with their booking by providing their personal information and payment details. The payment details are then sent to the payment service for processing.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Once payment has been processed successfully, the room reservation is confirmed by sending confirmation messages to both the customer and room services. At this point, all steps have been completed successfully, and the transaction can be considered complete.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading {"level":3} -->
<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Defining Steps and Actions</h3>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Each step in this booking process involves one or more actions that need to be performed by one or more services. For example, checking availability involves querying data from both customer and room services.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Similarly, processing payments requires communication between multiple services such as payment gateway providers or banks. Each action must be completed successfully before proceeding to the next step.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading {"level":3} -->
<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Coordinating Actions with the Saga Execution Coordinator</h3>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>As each step is completed, the services involved in that step communicate with the saga execution coordinator to indicate success or failure. If any step fails, the coordinator can initiate compensating actions to undo any changes made during previous steps and ensure that the transaction remains consistent.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>For example, if payment processing fails for any reason, then the coordinator can initiate a compensating action to cancel the room reservation and refund any payment made by the customer.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading -->
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Implementing Saga Orchestration Pattern: Best Practices and Tips</h2>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:heading {"level":3} -->
<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Use Event Sourcing to Ensure Consistency</h3>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:image {"id":61,"sizeSlug":"full","linkDestination":"none"} -->
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img src="/assets/blog/posts/imgs/event-sourcing.png" alt="Event sourcing" class="wp-image-61"/></figure>
<!-- /wp:image -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p><a href="/event-sourcing-beginners-guide/">Event sourcing</a> is a powerful tool that can help you ensure consistency in a distributed system. By storing all events that lead to a particular state, you can easily roll back to a previous state if something goes wrong during the execution of a saga.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>When using <a href="/event-sourcing-c-sharp/">event sourcing</a>, each change made to the system is recorded as an event. These events are then stored in an event log or database. When reconstructing the current state of the system, all events leading up to the current state are replayed.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>This approach has several benefits. First, it allows you to easily roll back to a previous state if something goes wrong during the execution of a saga. Second, it provides an audit trail of all changes made to the system. Finally, it enables you to build complex queries and analytics on top of your event data.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading {"level":3} -->
<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Include Rollback Events in Your Sagas</h3>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Rollback events are events that undo the effects of previous events. Including rollback events in your sagas can help you recover from errors or failures during the execution of a saga.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>For example, suppose you have a saga that involves creating an order and charging a customer's credit card. If there is an error while charging the credit card, you need to be able to undo any changes made up until that point.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>To do this, you could include a rollback event that reverses the charge on the customer's credit card. This would allow you to recover from errors and continue with the rest of your saga.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading {"level":3} -->
<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Keep Order Fulfillment Microservice Independent</h3>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The order fulfillment microservice should be independent of other services in your system. This means that it should not rely on other services to complete its tasks.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>By keeping it independent, you can ensure that it can handle failures and errors gracefully. For example, if one service fails or becomes unavailable, your order fulfillment microservice should still be able to fulfill orders using its own internal logic.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>To achieve this, you should design your order fulfillment microservice to be self-contained and resilient. It should have its own database and be able to handle errors and failures without relying on other services.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading {"level":3} -->
<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Test Your Sagas Thoroughly</h3>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Testing is crucial when implementing sagas. You should test each step of the saga to ensure that it works as expected. You should also test for failure scenarios to ensure that your sagas can handle errors and recover gracefully.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>For example, suppose you have a saga that involves creating an order, charging a customer's credit card, and shipping the order. To test this saga, you would need to simulate different scenarios such as:</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:list -->
<ul><!-- wp:list-item -->
<li>A successful order creation</li>
<!-- /wp:list-item -->

<!-- wp:list-item -->
<li>An unsuccessful credit card charge</li>
<!-- /wp:list-item -->

<!-- wp:list-item -->
<li>A successful credit card charge but unsuccessful shipping</li>
<!-- /wp:list-item -->

<!-- wp:list-item -->
<li>A successful saga execution</li>
<!-- /wp:list-item --></ul>
<!-- /wp:list -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>By testing these scenarios, you can ensure that your sagas are robust and can handle errors gracefully.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading -->
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Advantages of Saga Pattern: Database per Service and Orchestration Pattern</h2>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:heading {"level":3} -->
<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Database per Service and Orchestration Pattern: Advantages of Saga Pattern</h3>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Microservice architecture has become a popular approach to designing complex software systems. By breaking down monolithic applications into smaller, more manageable microservices, developers can achieve greater flexibility, scalability, and resilience. However, designing microservices architecture can be challenging, especially when dealing with multiple services that need to work together to complete transactions. That's where the saga pattern comes in.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->


<p>The saga pattern is a way of managing transactions across multiple microservices in a distributed system. It provides a mechanism for ensuring that all services involved in a transaction are executed in the correct order and that any errors or inconsistencies are handled gracefully. The saga pattern consists of two main components: the database per service approach and the orchestration pattern.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Database per Service Approach</h3>


<img src="/assets/blog/posts/imgs/database-per-service.png" alt="Database per service pattern"/>

<p>In traditional monolithic systems, there is usually one central database that stores all the data for the entire application. This can make it difficult to scale the system or make changes without affecting other parts of the application. In contrast, microservices architecture typically involves breaking down an application into smaller services that each have their own data store.</p>



<p>The database per service approach means that each microservice has its own database system that stores only the data it needs to function. This makes it easier to maintain and scale the system because changes made to one service won't affect other services or their data stores.</p>


<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>For example, imagine an e-commerce platform with several different microservices such as inventory management, order processing, payment processing, and shipping logistics. Each of these services would have its own database system that stores only the relevant information for that service. This allows developers to make changes or updates to one service without affecting other parts of the application.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading {"level":3} -->
<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Orchestration Pattern</h3>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The orchestration pattern is another important component of saga pattern. It ensures that all services involved in a transaction are executed in the correct order and that any errors or inconsistencies are handled gracefully. In other words, it provides a way to manage the flow of transactions across multiple microservices.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The orchestration pattern involves breaking down a transaction into smaller steps or sub-transactions, each of which is executed by a different microservice. The saga coordinator is responsible for managing the flow of these sub-transactions and ensuring that they are executed in the correct order.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>For example, imagine a customer placing an order on an e-commerce platform. This would involve several different microservices such as inventory management, payment processing, and shipping logistics. The orchestration pattern would ensure that each of these services is executed in the correct order to complete the transaction successfully.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading {"level":3} -->
<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Advantages of Saga Pattern</h3>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>One of the main advantages of saga pattern is that it simplifies the design and management of complex microservice architectures. By providing a way to manage transactions across multiple microservices, developers can avoid many of the pitfalls associated with distributed systems such as race conditions, deadlocks, and inconsistent data.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Another advantage is that saga pattern provides a mechanism for rolling back transactions if something goes wrong. If one service fails during a transaction, the entire process can be rolled back without affecting other microservices or data stores. This ensures that data remains consistent even in the event of errors or failures.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The inventory microservice and order service are two examples of services that can benefit from using saga pattern. These services often need to work together to complete transactions such as placing orders or updating inventory levels. By using saga pattern, developers can ensure that these transactions are executed correctly and consistently.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Saga pattern is particularly useful for breaking down monolithic systems into smaller, more manageable microservices. It allows developers to focus on individual services rather than trying to manage everything at once. This makes it easier to scale and maintain complex software systems over time.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading -->
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Challenges of Distributed Transactions: What You Need to Know</h2>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Implementing distributed transactions can be a challenging task for developers. Distributed transactions involve managing multiple participants and ensuring data consistency across all nodes. Local transactions may not always be sufficient for certain operations that involve multiple participants, making distributed transactions necessary.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>One of the biggest challenges in implementing distributed transactions is ensuring data consistency across all nodes. When a transaction is initiated, it must be completed successfully on all participating nodes to ensure data consistency. If any node fails to complete the transaction successfully, the entire transaction must be rolled back to maintain data consistency.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Compensating transactions are often used in distributed transaction scenarios to provide a way to undo or reverse the effects of a failed overall transaction or compensation transaction. Compensating transactions are designed to restore the system to its original state before the failed transaction occurred.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading {"level":4} -->
<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Challenges to keep in mind when using a saga pattern</h4>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The complexity of managing multiple participants in a distributed transaction can also pose significant challenges. Each participant may have different requirements and constraints that need to be taken into account during the implementation process. For example, some participants may require additional security measures or specific payment methods.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Another challenge in implementing distributed transactions is managing communication between nodes. Communication delays can occur due to network latency or other factors, which can lead to inconsistent data states across different nodes.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>To overcome these challenges, developers need to carefully plan and design their distributed transaction systems. They should consider factors such as data consistency, communication protocols, and compensating transactions when designing their systems.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>In addition, developers should also consider using tools and frameworks that provide transaction management capabilities for their distributed systems. These tools can help simplify the implementation process by providing pre-built components for handling common tasks such as error handling and compensation.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>When implementing distributed transactions, it's important to keep in mind that local transactions may not always be sufficient for certain operations that involve multiple participants. In these cases, developers should consider using compensating transactions or other techniques to ensure data consistency across all nodes.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>One example of a scenario where local transactions may not be sufficient is in payment processing systems. Payment processing involves multiple participants, including the buyer, seller, and payment gateway. To ensure that the transaction is completed successfully, all participants must be involved in the transaction.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Compensating transactions can be used in payment processing scenarios to provide a way to undo or reverse the effects of a failed overall transaction or compensation transaction. For example, if a payment fails to go through due to an error on the buyer's end, a compensating transaction can be used to refund the buyer's money and restore the system to its original state before the failed transaction occurred.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading -->
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Real-Life Examples of Choreography-Based and Orchestration-Based Saga</h2>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Orchestration-based saga is a popular approach in which an orchestrator coordinates the various services involved in fulfilling a request. One example of orchestration-based saga is the online shopping experience. When a customer places an order, the orchestrator coordinates the various services involved in fulfilling the order, such as payment processing, inventory management, and shipping.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The advantage of orchestration-based saga is that it can offer better performance than choreography-based saga because the orchestrator can optimize the sequence of service calls to minimize latency and improve overall throughput. This means that requests are fulfilled faster and with fewer errors.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>On the other hand, choreography-based saga is another approach where services communicate with each other to complete a transaction without relying on an orchestrator. A common example of choreography-based saga is ride-sharing services like Uber or Lyft. When a rider requests a ride, the various services involved in fulfilling the request, such as driver availability, GPS tracking, and payment processing, communicate with each other to complete the transaction.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>The advantage of choreography-based saga over orchestration-based saga is that it can offer better fault tolerance because there is no single point of failure. If one service fails, the other services can continue to operate independently.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>However, some real-life examples use a hybrid approach that combines elements of both choreography-based and orchestration-based saga. For example, a travel booking website might use an orchestrator to coordinate the various services involved in booking a trip (flights, hotels, rental cars), but rely on choreography between those services to handle changes or cancellations.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>When choosing between choreography and orchestration for your application's needs depends on factors such as performance requirements and fault tolerance needs. It's important to carefully evaluate these factors when designing a saga pattern for your real-life application.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading {"level":4} -->
<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Performance Benefits of Orchestration-Based Saga</h4>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Orchestration-Based Saga offers several advantages over Choreography-Based Saga. The orchestrator can optimize the sequence of service calls to minimize latency and improve overall throughput, which means that requests are fulfilled faster and with fewer errors. This approach is ideal for applications that require high performance, such as online shopping experiences.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading {"level":4} -->
<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Performance Benefits of Choreography-Based Saga</h4>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Choreography-Based Saga offers better fault tolerance than Orchestration-Based Saga because there is no single point of failure. If one service fails, the other services can continue to operate independently. This approach is ideal for applications that require high fault tolerance, such as ride-sharing services.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading {"level":4} -->
<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Hybrid Approach</h4>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Some real-life examples use a hybrid approach that combines elements of both Choreography-Based and Orchestration-Based Saga. For example, a travel booking website might use an orchestrator to coordinate the various services involved in booking a trip (flights, hotels, rental cars), but rely on choreography between those services to handle changes or cancellations.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading -->
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Final Thoughts on Saga Pattern and Its Applications</h2>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>In conclusion, understanding the saga pattern is crucial for designing robust and scalable applications. While two-phase commit (PC) pattern has been widely used in distributed transactions, it has several limitations that make it unsuitable for modern microservices architectures. The saga pattern offers an alternative approach that overcomes these limitations and provides a more flexible and reliable way to manage complex transactions.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading {"level":4} -->
<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Challenges of Saga pattern</h4>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>However, implementing the saga pattern requires careful planning and consideration of various factors such as service boundaries, message routing, compensation logic, and error handling. There are two ways to implement the saga pattern: choreography-based and orchestration-based. Both approaches have their advantages and drawbacks, depending on the specific use case.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Choreography-based sagas allow services to communicate with each other directly without relying on a central coordinator. This approach promotes loose coupling between services but can be challenging to debug when things go wrong. On the other hand, orchestration-based sagas rely on a central coordinator to manage the transaction flow between services. This approach provides better visibility into the transaction status but can introduce a single point of failure.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Despite its challenges, the saga pattern has several advantages that make it an attractive architecture pattern for modern microservices applications. One key advantage is database per service, which allows each service to have its own database instance instead of sharing a common database with other services. This approach improves scalability and reduces contention issues when multiple services access the same data.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:heading {"level":4} -->
<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Advantages of Saga pattern</h4>
<!-- /wp:heading -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>Another advantage of the saga pattern is its ability to support different types of transactions, including long-running transactions that span multiple requests or even days or weeks. The compensation logic in sagas enables applications to recover from failures gracefully by undoing previous actions or applying compensating actions.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->

<!-- wp:paragraph -->
<p>In real-life scenarios, there are many examples of how companies have successfully implemented choreography-based or orchestration-based sagas in their applications. For instance, Uber uses choreography-based sagas for managing ride requests and payments, while Zalando uses orchestration-based sagas for order processing and fulfillment.</p>
<!-- /wp:paragraph -->]]>
  </content>
</post>